Guide to the John Ferrone Papers MSS.411
Fales Library and Special Collections
John Ferrone Papers
1942-2012
Fales Library and Special Collections
MSS.411
3.5 Linear Feet in 7 manuscript boxes
John Ferrone (August 14, 1924 – April 10, 2016) was an American book editor working for Dell Publishing and Harcourt, Brace, & World (later Harcourt Brace Jovanovich). Ferrone retired from Harcourt Brace Jovanovich in 1990, but over his lengthy career, he had numerous high profile clients including: Eudora Welty, Anais Nin, Helen McCully, C.S. Lewis, Alice Walker, and James Beard. Ferrone's close friendship with James Beard led to much collaboration in the kitchen, as well as in the publication world. After James Beard's death in 1985, Ferrone served as Beard's literary executor. The John Ferrone Collection roughly spans from 1942 to 2012, with the bulk of the materials dating between 1970 to the early 1990s. This collection contains correspondence; press-clippings containing articles, essays, and columns written by James Beard; and article and manuscript drafts. Most of the materials relate to James Beard, however, there are also papers related to Ferrone's other clients as well.
Scope and Contents
The John Ferrone Papers roughly span from 1942 to 2012, with the bulk of the materials dating between 1970 to the early 1990s. This collection contains correspondence; press-clippings containing articles, essays, and recipes written by James Beard; and manuscripts for books edited by Ferrone.
The majority of this collection relates to cookbook author and chef, James Beard, one of Ferrone's biggest clients and closest friends. Ferrone kept a record of his personal and business collaboration with James Beard over several decades by saving their correspondence as well as copies of works written by Beard including magazine articles, columns, essays, and drafts.
In addition to Ferrone's correspondence with Beard, the correspondence files also include papers related to Ferrone's role as literary executor of Beard's estate, including correspondence with various publishers and book distributors regarding royalties and licensing fees. Ferrone also saved his correspondences with the Chalfont Agency, the literary agency in charge of the Beard Estate. Drafts of The Essential James Beard Cookbook, co-edited by Ferrone, are included in this collection. Additionally, Ferrone kept copies of Beard's correspondence with chef and cookbook author Helen Evans Brown. In 1994 Ferrone published Love and Kisses and a Halo of Truffles: Letters to Helen Evans Brown, an edited selection of letters from Beard and Brown's correspondence.
The rest of the correspondence files include information about John Ferrone's time working at and his departure from Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, as well as his communications with clients other than Beard. The clients represented in this collection were involved in literary projects that included the writings of Eudora Welty, Anaïs Nin, Jack London, Helen McCully, Virginia Woolf, Violet Trefusis, and C.S. Lewis. Ferrone did not work directly with all of these authors; in some cases he published lesser-known works, correspondences, and compilations created after the author's death.
This collection also includes the manuscript for Hellen McCully's Waste Not Want Not: A Cookbook of Delicious Foods from Leftovers published in 1975.
Biographical note
John Ferrone (August 14, 1924 – April 10, 2016) was an American book editor working for Dell Publishing and Harcourt, Brace, & World (later Harcourt Brace Jovanovich). Ferrone retired from Harcourt Brace Jovanovich in 1990, but over his lengthy career, he had numerous high profile clients including: Eudora Welty, Anais Nin, Helen McCully, C.S. Lewis, Alice Walker, and James Beard. Ferrone's close friendship with James Beard led to much collaboration in the kitchen, as well as in the publication world. After James Beard's death in 1985, Ferrone served as Beard's literary executor.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received at the time of purchase.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from James Cummins Booksellers in 2014. The accession number associated with this acquisition is 2014.411.
Related Materials
For more information about John Ferrone's professional and personal relationship with James Beard see John Ferrone's interview included in Voices from the Food Revolution: People Who Changed The Way Americans Eat: An oral history project conducted by Judith Weinraub (MSS.309).
For more information on the life and career of James Beard please see the James Beard Foundation Archive (MSS.214), the James Beard Papers (MSS.263), and the James Beard Collection (MSS.139).
Food writers.; Cookbooks.; Food writing.; Publishers and publishing; Beard, James, 1903-1985; Brown, Helen Evans; Harcourt Brace Jovanovich
- Correspondence--James Beard, 1964-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence--Lee Kessler, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence--Walter Hooper, 1982-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence--William Hathaway, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence--John Phillips, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence--Mitchell Leaska, 1983-1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence--Professional, 1964-1998 (Box 1, Folder 7-14)
- Correspondence-- Menus for Entertaining, 1986-1995 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
- Book cover proofs, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- "Beard on Food" Syndicated Column, 1966-1983 (Box 2, Folder 4-9)
- James Beard's writing on Lunching, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- James Beard's writing on Eating Out, 1966-1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- James Beard's writing on Menu Planning, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- James Beard's writing on Chefs, 1964-1974 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- James Beard's writing on the Kitchen, 1968-1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- James Beard's writing on American Cookery, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- James Beard's writing in American Way, 1975-1981 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- James Beard's writing in Bon Appetit, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- James Beard's writing in Diversion, 1969-1983 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
- James Beard's writing in House and Garden, 1965-1976 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- James Beard's writing in Harper's Bazaar, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- James Beard's writing in Argrosy, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- James Beard's writing in House Beautiful, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- James Beard's writing in McCall's, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- James Beard's writing in the New York Times, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- James Beard's writing in The Pleasure of Cooking, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- James Beard's writing in New York Magazine, 1974-1977 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- James Beard's writing in Style, 1973-1980 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- James Beard's writing in Travel and Leisure, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- James Beard's writing in Town and Country, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- James Beard's writing in Today's Woman, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
- James Beard's writing in Woman's Day, 1974-1981 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Homemaking with a Flair by James Beard, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- James Beard draft essays, 1975-1981 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Unpublished articles by James Beard, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Draft of Waste Not, Want Not Cookbook: The Art of Lively Leftovers by Helen McCully -- Draft, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- The Essential James Beard Cookbook -- Drafts, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 5-7)
- Beard to Brown: A Mostly Culinary Correspondence -- Manuscript, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 2-6)
- Correspondence -- Helen Evans Brown and James Beard, 1952-1964 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Correspondence -- Helen Evans Brown and James Beard, 1952-1964 (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
- Correspondence -- Helen Evans Brown and James Beard, 1952-1964 (Box 7, Folder 1-5)